Thies Gehrmann PhD Curriculum Vitæ

(email): thiesgehrmann@gmail.com (https): thiesgehrmann.github.io (tel NL): +31 (0)640 175 860

D.O.B. April 8^{th} 1989 Nationality: German Private address: Morskade 14 2332 GB Leiden The Netherlands

Last updated December 11, 2019.

Personal profile

Currently, I am a Postdoc in the department of Molecular Epidemiology at the Leiden University Medical Centre, working on translational research of healthy ageing. Bioinformatics is a constantly developing field, with continuously evolving measurements that presents a splendid opportunity to develop and apply novel methods. It also requires the practitioner to develop multidisciplinary skills from the statistical, computational and biological domains. I am excited to be part of this field, where my knowledge and competences are constantly challenged, humbled and developed.

Employment

Jan. 2018 -Present Postdoc at Department of Molecular Epidemiology, Leiden University Medical Centre Bioinformatician on healthy ageing, together with Max Plank Institute of Biological Ageing. Within the ERC funded "Geroprotect" project.

Nov. 2016 - 2017

Postdoc at KNAW/Westerdijk Institute of Fungal Biodiversity $Embedded\ bioinformatician.$

Nov. 2012 - 2016

PhD Candidate

Conducted research and performed teaching. Within the STW funded "Push the white button" project.

Education

2012-2018

Pattern Recognition and Bioinformatics group, TU Delft, The Netherlands $PhD\ in\ Bioinformatics.$

Bioinformatic Analysis of Genetic and Transcriptomic Variation in Fungi.

2010-2012

Leiden University, Leiden, The Netherlands (In cooperation with TU Delft)

 $MSc\ Computer\ Science\ Track\ Bioinformatics.$

Thesis on protein function prediction using Conditional Random Fields.

2008-2010

Heriot Watt University, Edinburgh, Scotland

BSc (Ord) Computer Science

Graduated with distinction.

2007-2008

Napier University, Edinburgh, Scotland

Certificate of Higher Education

Completed year 1 of Computer Studies, then transferred to Heriot Watt University.

Skills

Analytical

Machine learning and statistics; "Data Science".

Analysis of Sanger, NGS and long-read sequencing data (genomic, transcriptomic, epigenomic).

Genetic/Genomic analysis (Genome assembly, Linkage analysis, *-WAS & *-QTL, \mathcal{C}

Comparative genomics, Phylogenetic analysis, Variant calling)

Transcriptomic analysis (Differential expression, Alternative splicing, Variant calling, eQTL analysis, Timeseries analysis).

Epigenetic analysis (Methylation), and metabolomic data.

Technical Python, Scala, C/C++, Java, Shell, Matlab, R

SQL, XML (and related technologies), LATEX.

Vector image editing (Inkscape, Affinity Designer).

Pipeline development and management (Snakemake, Workflow Description Language,

Anaconda, Jupyter Notebook).

Experience with schedulers (SLURM, PDB) and version control software, (Git, SVN).

Experienced with Unix environments (Linux, MacOS).

Languages Native speaker, English Norwegian and German.

High level Dutch. Beginners French.

Referees

Upon request Contact Thies for referee contact details.

Teaching

MSc Courses | Frontiers of Science

Teaching assistant. Fall 2019 at Leiden University Medical Center.

Functional Genomics and Systems Biology

Lecturer and teaching assistant. Fall 2014, 2015, and 2016 at TU Delft

Computational Molecular Biology

Teaching assistant. Spring 2012 at Leiden University

BSc Courses Biomedical Informatics

Lecturer. Fall 2019 at Leiden University Medical Center.

Clinical Research in Practice

Lecturer. Fall 2019 at Leiden University Medical Center.

 ${\it Clinical \ Biotechnology: \ Bioinformatics}$

Teaching assistant. Fall 2018, 2019 at TU Delft.

Molecular Data Science

Teaching assistant. Spring 2018 at Leiden University Medical Center

Life Science and Technology Bioinformatics Teaching assistant. Spring 2016 at TU Delft.

Genome Scale Data Analysis

Lecturer and teaching assistant. Fall 2014 at TU Delft

External Courses | Quantitative biology summer school

Lectured on computational aspects of synteny and alternative splicing in fungi.

Summer 2015 at Utrecht University.

Student Supervision

Myrthe de Haan | B.Sc student 2019-2020

Using the drug-protein interactome to predict intervention-mimicing drugs.

Jet Beekwilder | B.Sc Student 2017-2018

Comparison of DNA extraction methods from fungi for Nanopore sequencing.

André Vollering | M.Sc Student 2014-2015

Heterosis: Finding Associated Genomic Regions. (Under embargo)

Valerie Pourquie | B.Sc Student 2015

Conservation of polarization proteins in yeast and fungi.

Dimitris M.Sc Student 2013-2014

Palachanis Using the Multiple Instance Learning framework to address differential regulation.

Other activities/skills/information

Awards Nature Ageing, Rejuvination and Health Conference 2019, 'Best Poster' award.

ECCB 2016 Student Symposium, 'Best Oral Presentation' award.

Benelux Bioinformatics Conference 2015 Student Symposium, 'Best Oral

presentation'.

TU Delft Graduate School, 'Best poster presentation' award 2013.

Scott Logic Computer Science Prize 2010.

Reviewing Publons profile

Nature Communications (2019)

Bioinformatics (2019)

Nature Scientific Reports (2019) FEMS Yeast Research (2018) Nucleic Acid Research (2016)

Volunteering International Student Network (Leiden) 2013-2019. Set construction and management.

Dutch Red Cross (Den Haag) 2014-2015. First Aid (EHBO) at events and refugee

centers.

Hackathons Hackathon for Good 2019, The Hague: Translators Without Borders challenge

Hackathon for Good 2018, The Hague: Asser Lang-grabbing challenge

Publications

Journal publications

Google Scholar profile

- Vladimiro Guarnaccia, Thies Gehrmann, Geraldo J. Silvia-Junior, Paul H.
 Fourie, Sajeet Haridas, Duong Vu, Joseph Spatafora, Francis M Martin, Vincent Robert, Igor V. Grigoriev, Johannes Z. Groenewald, and Pedro W. Crous.
 Phyllosticta citricarpa and sister species of global importance to citrus.
 Molecular Plant Pathology, 2019
- [2] D Vu, Marizeth Groenewald, M De Vries, T Gehrmann, B Stielow, U Eberhardt, A Al-Hatmi, JZ Groenewald, G Cardinali, J Houbraken, et al. Large-scale generation and analysis of filamentous fungal dna barcodes boosts coverage for kingdom fungi and reveals thresholds for fungal species and higher taxon delimitation. Studies in mycology, 92:135–154, 2019
- [3] Eveline T Diepeveen, Thies Gehrmann, Valérie Pourquié, Thomas Abeel, and Liedewij Laan. Patterns of conservation and diversification in the fungal polarization network. *Genome biology and evolution*, 10(7):1765–1782, 2018
- [4] Thies Gehrmann, Jordi F Pelkmans, Robin A Ohm, Aurin M Vos, Anton SM Sonnenberg, Johan JP Baars, Han AB Wösten, Marcel JT Reinders, and Thomas Abeel. Nucleus-specific expression in the multinuclear mushroom-forming fungus agaricus bisporus reveals different nuclear regulatory programs. Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences, 115(17):4429–4434, 2018
- [5] Francine Boonekamp, Sofia Dashko, Marcel Van den Broek, Thies Gehrmann, Jean-Marc Daran, and Pascale Daran-Lapujade. The genetic makeup and expression of the glycolytic and fermentative pathways are highly conserved within the saccharomyces genus. Frontiers in genetics, 9:504, 2018
- [6] Abigail L Manson, Thomas Abeel, James E Galagan, Jagadish Chandrabose Sundaramurthi, Alex Salazar, Thies Gehrmann, Siva Kumar Shanmugam, Kannan Palaniyandi, Sujatha Narayanan, Soumya Swaminathan, et al. Mycobacterium tuberculosis whole genome sequences from southern india suggest novel resistance mechanisms and the need for region-specific diagnostics. Clinical Infectious Diseases, 64(11):1494-1501, 2017
- [7] Jordi F Pelkmans, Mohini B Patil, Thies Gehrmann, Marcel JT Reinders, Han AB Wösten, and Luis G Lugones. Transcription factors of schizophyllum commune involved in mushroom formation and modulation of vegetative growth. Scientific reports, 7(1):310, 2017
- [8] Thies Gehrmann, Jordi F Pelkmans, Luis G Lugones, Han AB Wösten, Thomas Abeel, and Marcel JT Reinders. Variants in rna-seq data show a continued mutation rate during strain preservation of schizophyllum commune. *BioRxiv*, page 201012, 2017
- [9] Jordi F Pelkmans, Aurin M Vos, Karin Scholtmeijer, Ed Hendrix, Johan JP Baars, Thies Gehrmann, Marcel JT Reinders, Luis G Lugones, and Han AB Wösten. The transcriptional regulator c2h2 accelerates mushroom formation in agaricus bisporus. Applied microbiology and biotechnology, 100(16):7151-7159, 2016
- [10] Thies Gehrmann and Marcel JT Reinders. Proteny: discovering and visualizing statistically significant syntenic clusters at the proteome level. Bioinformatics, 31(21):3437-3444, 2015

Conference

[11] Thies Gehrmann, Marco Loog, Marcel JT Reinders, and Dick de Ridder.

publications

Conditional random fields for protein function prediction. In IAPR International Conference on Pattern Recognition in Bioinformatics, pages 184–195. Springer, Berlin, Heidelberg, 2013

Under Review

[12] Design and experimental evaluation of a minimal, innocuous watermarking strategy to distinguish near-identical DNA and RNA sequences. ($Under\ review\ in\ ACS\ Synthetic\ Biology)$

In Progress

- [13] A combined lifestyle intervention induces a sensitization of the blood transcriptomic response to a nutrient challenge (*In progress*)
- [14] Characterization of genetic variants in RAS/MEK/ERK Pathway in exceptionally long-lived Dutch families (*In progress*)
- [15] Characterization of genetic variants in Linkage regions identified in exceptionally long-lived Dutch families (*In progress*)
- [16] Antonis Somarakis, Manolis Fragkiadakis, Marios Kefalas, Stelios Paraschiakos, Michaelis Vrachasotakis, Thies Gehrmann. On the global prediction of land grabbing risk. (*Under review in Land*)
- [17] Annick Lang, Thies Gehrmann, Nils Cronberg. Genetic diversity in bryophyte population with facultative nannandry (*In progress*)

Talks

Conference talks

2019

DUSRA 2019: Presenter

A combined lifestyle intervention induces a sex-specific sensitization of the blood transcriptomic response to a nutrient challenge

LANDac 2019: Panel organizer and presenter

Uniting Global and Hyper-Local Data for Land: The use of global and local data for land grabbing risk prediction

European Dialogue on Internet Governance, Euro
DIG 2019: Panel organizer and presenter $\,$

Digital cooperation in action - A collaborative case study: Predicting Land Grabbing

BioSB 2019: Presenter

 $Nutrient\ challenge\ exposes\ transcriptomic\ shift\ by\ lifestyle\ intervention\ in\ healthy\ participants$

2016 ECCB Student Symposium 2016: Presenter

Karyollele specific expression in Agaricus bisporus

2015 BBC Student Symposium 2015: Presenter

Alternative Splicing in mushrooms from RNA-Seq

2013 Pattern Recognition in Bioinformatics 2013: Presenter

Conditional Random Fields for protein function prediction

Invited talks

2014

Heriot Watt University, Computer Science Seminar Series

Detecting and visualizing statistically significant clusters of conserved genes of diverged genomes.

Conference Organization

2019

LANDac 2019: Panel organizer
Uniting Global and Hyper-Local Data for Land

European Dialogue on Internet Governance, EuroDIG 2019: Panel organizer

Digital cooperation in action - A collaborative case study